A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, The Fund for Adult Education (FAE) records FA716
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, The Fund for Adult Education (FAE) records
1951-1972
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA716
9.24 Cubic Feet
Related Archival Materials note
A portion of the records of the Ford Foundation Fund for Adult Education, is located in Syracuse University's Special Collections Research Center.
Biographical/Historical note
The Fund for Adult Education was established by the Ford Foundation on April 5, 1951, as part of the Foundation's redefined and expanded activities following the final settlement of the estates of Henry and Edsel Ford in l950. The new President of the Foundation, former Marshall Plan administrator Paul G. Hoffman, and his Associate Director Robert M. Hutchins, established several semi-autonomous funds, including the Fund for the Advancement of Education and the Fund for Adult Education. The Funds were intended to obtain large-scale results quickly and to help the Ford Foundation avoid violating federal laws which forbade tax-exempt foundations from accumulating "unreasonable" surpluses. The Fund for the Advancement of Education would be concerned with problems and opportunities in education in a more formalized structure whereas the Fund for Adult Education would devote itself to "that part of the educational process which begins when formal schooling is finished."*
The Fund for Adult Education was organized as a non-profit membership corporation in the State of New York with a Board of Member-Directors comprised of fifteen citizens from business, education, agriculture, and labor. Board members included Charles H. Percy, Milton S. Eisenhower, Marion B. Folsom, Sarah Gibson Blanding, and Clarence Francis. They met three to four times a year to set policy, discuss programs, and approve grants. FAE's staff was not a large one, averaging about fifteen administrators plus occasional outside consultants. Originally located in Pasadena, California, FAE moved to New York in l956. FAE would fund programs to meet its goal of enabling adults to continue their education in the humanities and political affairs which, in turn, would make them better informed citizens. * Ten Year Report, pp. 10-12.
FAE's Annual Reports and final Ten Year Report provide background information on the main goals and accomplishments of FAE and its grantees as well as a list of Board and staff members. By the time of its termination in 1961, FAE had been granted $47.4 million by the Ford Foundation for its activities. In the first five years of its existence, FAE played a major role in the early development of public television stations and programming with grants totaling more than $11 million. It funded the National Citizens Committee for Educational Television, Joint Committee on Educational Television, and National Association of Educational Broadcasters, who together helped educational television stations acquire licenses, obtain community support, and construct facilities. In 1952, FAE received a Ford Foundation grant which established the (National) Educational Television and Radio Center (ETRC) at Ann Arbor to supply programming to stations across the nation. FAE continued to support ETRC until 1956 when broad institutional support for educational television development was shifted to direct Ford Foundation control following the report of a Joint FAE/Foundation Study headed by Justice Arthur T. Vanderbilt. After the study, FAE concentrated its adult education programs through existing institutions of higher learning.
A second major effort of FAE was to develop a series of study-discussion programs as a method of bringing adults together with trained program leaders to discuss such topics as American History, the arts, and world affairs and to create a body of materials that could be published and used nationwide. FAE supported local and national organizations who designed and conducted programs using educational television and the discussion method at cities around the country. An internal study of the discussion program, Accent on Learning: An Analytic History of the Fund for Adult Education's Experimental Discussion Project. 1951-1959.
FAE's final project was "Education for Public Responsibility," begun in 1958. At that time, a debate was raging in American education following the Russian launch of Sputnik I in October 1957. While many stressed the need to expand scientific and technical education, others argued that the Soviet challenge could best be met by a liberal arts education where laymen and scientists would have a broad understanding of each other. To this end, FAE made grants of $1.5 million to universities and professional organizations for programs, conferences, and fellowships to prepare young and middle level professionals to face contemporary problems and issues. (see Archives Catalog), was conducted by Dr. Glen Burch. FAE also created or expanded the continuing education divisions of many American and Canadian universities.
FAE had been established in a climate of enthusiasm for the Foundation's potential to advance human welfare in many areas. However, throughout the life of FAE, there was disagreement among the Ford trustees over the merits of decentralized funds, with separate Boards of Directors and staffs, broad mandates, and multi-million dollar budgets. By 1953, after the resignation of Paul Hoffman, the Foundation was in a period of transition in which Board members and staff who advocated more direct supervision of fund programs by the Foundation began to prevail. Influencing this trend was the publicity being given to Congressional hearings by the Cox and Reece Committees investigating tax-exempt foundations. These hearings, conducted in 1952 and 1954, highlighted existing criticism about the Foundation's autonomous funds.
Following several evaluations of FAE, by consultant Ralph Tyler in l952 and Ford Vice President Dyke Brown in 1954 and 1959, and the Vanderbilt Report of 1955, Foundation officials concluded in late 1959, that the $17.5 million grant for 1956 through 1961, would be FAE's terminal one. Several staff members of FAE would then join the education division of the Foundation, which had been created from the staff of the Fund for the Advancement of Education in 1957. A reconstituted caretaker Board of Directors, comprised of Ford Foundation staff, continued in existence to complete final distribution of grant moneys. This Board issued its final report in 1971. The corporation was dissolved legally on May 22, 1972.
Arrangement note
Series 1: ADMINISTRATIVE RECORDS. Subseries 1: Meetings to the Board of Directors: Minutes, Dockets and Agendas. Subseries 2: Mailings to the Board. Subseries 3: FAE Office Files. Subseries 4: Photographs. Subseries 5: Office Files of G.H. Griffith.
Series 2: FINANCIAL, LEGAL, AND TAX RECORDS.
Conditions Governing Access note
Collection is open for scholarly research with select material restricted as noted.
Series 1 is open for scholarly research. Series 2 is restricted from scholarly access.
Series 3 is open for scholarly research, as microfilm only.
Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Fund for Adult Education (FAE) document the administrative activities and the financial and legal concerns of the Fund's mission.
- Administrative records, 1950-1972; I
  Arrangement
  Series 1, Administrative Records consists of five subseries: 1) Meetings of the Board of Directors, 2) Mailings to the Board of Directors, 3) Office Files, 4) Photographs, and 5) files of G.H. Griffiths, who served as FAE's Vice President, Secretary, and Treasurer.
  - Board of Directors, Minutes, Dockets, Agendas, 1951-1961; 1
    Scope and Contents
    Subseries 1, Meetings of the Board of Directors.
    Information files in Boxes 1-5 contain an almost complete set of Board dockets and unsigned minutes from its first meeting on April 5, 1951 to the last meeting of the independent Board on November 7, 1961. The minutes of each meeting include minutes of the Executive Committee of the Board which met on the same dates. (Six sets of Minutes are missing from the information files). The dockets for each meeting, which consist of agenda for the meetings, background material for grants to be approved, and supporting documentation, are complete. In the early meetings of 1951 and January 1952, and that of June 24, 1954, there were no printed dockets. Supplemental documents to the docket and minutes include additional reports, financial projections, and correspondence for discussion at Board meetings.
    Early minutes discuss initial organizational matters and reflect the enthusiasm of the Board for its task, especially the development of educational television stations and programming. As early as 1953, discussions of FAE's relationship with the Ford Foundation appear in FAE Board minutes, especially as each large Foundation grant to FAE came up for approval by Foundation trustees. Major grants to FAE were approved by the Ford trustees in April 1951, February 1952, July 1952, February 1953, September 1953, May 1954, and December 1955. FAE Board meetings of October 1953 and April, June, and October 1954, are particularly relevant for discussions of FAE goals, accomplishments, and long-term plans. The meeting of October 1955, reflects FAE's response to the transfer of responsibility for educational television development to the Ford Foundation following the Joint Study (Vanderbilt Report). A copy of the Vanderbilt Report is included in the supplemental documents for the February 9, 1956 Board meeting.
    The Cox Committee hearings of 1952 and Reece Committee hearings of 1954 on tax-exempt foundations are both mentioned in the records. Following the Cox hearings, the October 1952 minutes express caution over the selection of grantees. Lengthy discussions of the Reece hearings are recorded in the May and October 1955 minutes. The charges of the Committee, as summarized by FAE's counsel, were that foundations concerned with education were engaged in propaganda "hostile to American traditions" and that a "huge cartel" composed of educational organizations and foundations dominated the field. The FAE Board found the Reece report to be lacking in objectivity and totally without merit.
    Throughout 1955 and 1956, the minutes discuss what was to become of the last $17.5 million grant to FAE, approved by the Ford Foundation trustees in December 1955. These discussions may be read in connection with FAE subject files in the Office Files of H. Rowan Gaither, President of the Ford Foundation from 1953 to 1956 (Box 2, folders 24-28 and Box 3, folders 29-34), Henry T. Heald, President from 1956 to 1965 (Box 4, folders 56-57), and William McPeak, Associate Director and Vice-President from 1953 to 1964 (Box 6, folders 173-176). The records of the February 1957 meeting are significant for a discussion of the consolidation of the Fund for the Advancement of Education's staff into the Ford Foundation. The 1958 meetings reflect the ongoing debates over American educational policies following the launch of Sputnik I, which in part resulted in FAE's Education for Public Responsibility program.
    - Minutes, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Agenda and Minutes, 1952 January 17-18 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1952 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1952 July 11 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1952 October 13-14 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Appendix to Docket, 1952 October 13-14 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1953 January 23-24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1953 May 28-29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1953 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1954 January 19-20 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Progress Reports on l953 Grants & Projects, 1954 January 19-20 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1954 April 23 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Minutes, 1954 June 20 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1954 October 28 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1955 January 20-21 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1955 May 27 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1955 October 26-27 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Executive Committee Docket and Minutes, 1956 February 9 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      Scope and Contents note
      Board did not meet.
    - Executive Committee Supplementary Documents (1955 December docket of Ford Trustees), 1956 February 9 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1956 May 24-25 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Supplementary Documents, 1956 May 24-25 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Docket, Minutes, and Supplementary Documents, 1956 October 29 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1957 February 11-12 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1957 May 20 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Docket, Minutes, and Supplementary Documents, 1957 October 29 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Docket, Minutes, and Supplementary Documents, 1958 January 20 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1958 May 13 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1958 October 19-22 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Supplementary Documents, 1958 October 19-22 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Docket, Minutes, and Supplementary Documents, 1959 January 19 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1959 May 17 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Supplementary Documents, 1959 May 17 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Docket, 1959 October 20 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Supplementary Reports, 1959 October 20 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Docket, 1960 January 19 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Docket, 1960 May 17 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Docket- Part I, 1960 November 15 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Docket- Part II and Supplementary Documents, 1960 November 15 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Docket, 1961 March 21 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Docket and Minutes, 1961 June 14 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Docket, 1961 November 7 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Mailings to the Board, 1951-1961; 2
    Subseries 2, Mailings to the Board (Boxes 6-10), contains material which was sent to Board members between meetings. These mailings, usually sent with an explanatory covering letter, include articles, clippings, speeches, reports, news releases, and pamphlets. They cover such topics as adult education issues, educational TV, FAE programs, and grantee programs. The section is arranged in its original chronological order to give a complete view of what the staff felt the Board should be reading on educational issues and the flow of information on FAE operations. The mailings include a staff-prepared table of contents for each of the first four years of the mailings (1951-1954).
    Of particular interest are speeches by Robert Hutchins (August 8, 1951, May 2, 1952, and February 18, 1955) and C. Scott Fletcher (March 10, 1953, Dec. 19, 1957, May 2, 1958, and March 29, 1961), and summaries of a joint seminar, conducted for the FAE and TFAE Boards by Mortimer Adler (January 2, April 10, 1952) and material on the Vanderbilt Study (1954 throughout and October 19, 1955) and Reece Committee (May 20 and June 1, 1955).
    - Table of Contents, 1951 March 29-April 23 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - 1951 April 24-1952 April 10 (Box 6, Folder 43-49)
    - 1952 April 16-1953 October 30 (Box 7, Folder 50-59)
    - 1953 November 17-1955 December 19 (Box 8, Folder 60-68)
    - 1956 January 11-1959 July 28 (Box 9, Folder 69-78)
    - 1959 August 5-1961 June 16 (Box 10, Folder 79-82)
  - FAE Office Files, 1950-1969; 3
    Subseries 3, Office Files (Boxes 11-17) consist of correspondence, memoranda, reports, surveys, speech transcripts, printed materials, and drafts produced by consultants, grantees, and FAE staff.
    Subjects include the disposition of the FAE facility in White Plains, several letters of C.S. Fletcher, correspondence and statements regarding the Ford Foundation grant to FAE, and FAE publications, News Digest, News Letter, and News Releases.
    Although both the mission and concerns of FAE are illustrated, the Office Files are limited and inconsistent in the types of material, chronology, and subject matter addressed. Furthermore, no files have been preserved for C. Scott Fletcher, the President of FAE. The result is a somewhat miscellaneous grouping of materials arranged alphabetically by both specific and general subject headings. Unless misleading, the original file title has been used. There is some overlap between portions of this material and the financial and grant records.
    Material on grantees, seminars, and FAE programs, such as the Great Books Foundation, is included. Notable are grantee and program surveys and evaluations by consultants and the management firms, McKinsey and Co. and Cresap, McCormick and Paget.
    - Agreements (Box 11)
      - California, Univ. of: University Extension, "The Ways of Mankind", 1958-1962 (Box 11, Folder 83)
      - Friend, Krueger and Callender: Advertising Agency, 1956-1958 (Box 11, Folder 84)
      - In Quest of Knowledge (C. Hartley Grattan), 1953; 1954; 1958 (Box 11, Folder 85)
      - McGraw-Hill Publishing Company, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 86)
      - Michigan State University, 1959-1962 (Box 11, Folder 87)
      - Monroe, Margaret, 1960-1961 (Box 11, Folder 88)
    - American College Public Relations Assoc. award, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 89)
    - Bibliographies: publications & related material, 1950s; 1963 (Box 11, Folder 90)
    - Bylaw amendment, 1960; 1963 (Box 11, Folder 91)
    - Change of Location Certificate, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 92)
    - Consultants:
      - Mazel, Inc., 1956-1958 (Box 11, Folder 93-96)
      - Clark, Ann, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 97)
      - Colbert, Roy, 1958 (Box 11, Folder 98)
      - Crohn, Richard J, 1959-1960 (Box 11, Folder 99)
      - Dennis, Lawrence E. ("Depth Interviews"), 1959-1961 (Box 11, Folder 100)
      - Fiske, Marjorie, 1955-1956 (Box 11, Folder 101)
      - Goldwin, Robert A., 1959-1961 (Box 11, Folder 102)
      - Grattan, C. Hartley, 1958-1960 (Box 11, Folder 103)
      - Hofstadter, Richard, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 104)
      - Mail Andrews Corp. of America, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 105)
      - Moss, Tobias, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 106)
      - Nelson Associates, (Charles A.), 1957-1961 (Box 11, Folder 107)
      - Nelson, C.M., 1951-1952 (Box 11, Folder 108)
      - Smith, Hilda W., 1951-1952 (Box 12, Folder 109)
      - Tyler, Ralph W., 1952-1955 (Box 12, Folder 110)
      - Walker, Turnley, 1952-1955 (Box 12, Folder 111)
      - Walker, Turnley (Surveys), 1954; 1955 (?) (Box 12, Folder 112-114)
    - Copyright and Royalty Agreements, 1953-1969 (Box 12, Folder 115)
    - Dreiman vs FAE, 1960 (?) (Box 12, Folder 116)
    - "Educational Television in the United States", 1957 (Box 12, Folder 117)
    - "Education for Public Responsibility", 1959; 1961 (Box 12, Folder 118)
    - Evaluations
    - Correspondence, Memoranda, and Polcy Statements, 1951-1954; 1956 (Box 12, Folder 119)
    - Cresap, McCormick and Paget: An Appraisal of FAE, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 120)
    - Cresap, McCormick and Paget: A Study of FAE Grantees, 1953 (Box 12, Folder 121)
    - Cresap, McCormick and Paget: The Board of Directors of the Film Council of America, 1953 (Box 12, Folder 122)
    - Cresap, McCormick and Paget: Film Council of America, 1953 (Box 13, Folder 123)
    - Cresap, McCormick and Paget: Inter Univ. Labor Educ. Committee (IULEC), 1954 (Box 13, Folder 124)
    - Cresap, McCormick and Paget: Test Cities Project, 1954 (Box 13, Folder 125)
    - Dale, Edgar, 1952 (Box 13, Folder 126)
    - McKinsey and Company: Adult Education Association of America, 1953 (Box 13, Folder 127)
    - McKinsey and Company: American Foundation for Political Education, 1954 (Box 13, Folder 128)
    - McKinsey and Company: Foreign Policy Association Program, 1953 (Box 13, Folder 129)
    - McKinsey and Company: The Great Books Foundation, 1953 (Box 13, Folder 130)
    - McKinsey and Company: Summary Report, 1954 (Box 13, Folder 131)
    - McKinsey and Company: Test Cities and Region Project, 1954 (Box 13, Folder 132)
    - Fletcher, C. Scott: Letters to C.H. Faust, 1952-1961 (Box 13, Folder 133)
    - Fletcher, C. Scott: Letters to H.R. Gaither, 1954 (Box 13, Folder 134)
    - Fletcher, C. Scott: Permissions to quote, 1958-1959 (Box 13, Folder 135)
    - Ford Foundation Grant, 1955 January-November 12 (Box 13, Folder 136)
    - Ford Foundation Grant, 1955 November 15-1958 July (Box 13, Folder 136)
    - Grantees
      - Akron, University of, 1959-1961 (Box 13, Folder 138)
      - Amer. Foundation for Continuing Educ., 1963-1967 (Box 14, Folder 139)
      - California, Univ. of: Northern Area, 1959-1961 (Box 14, Folder 140)
      - California, Univ. of: Southern Area, 1959-1961 (Box 14, Folder 141)
      - Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults, 1960-1963 (Box 14, Folder 142)
      - Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults: Clearing House, 1961 (Box 14, Folder 143)
      - Central Calif. Educational Television, 1955-1965 (Box 14, Folder 144)
      - Chicago, University of--Basic Program of Liberal, 1960-1962 (Box 14, Folder 145)
      - Chicago, University of--Workshops for Adult Educators, 1958-1962 (Box 14, Folder 146)
      - Committee for Economic Development, 1960-1961 (Box 14, Folder 147)
      - Great Books Foundation, 1952-1953; 1965 (Box 14, Folder 148)
      - New York Univ.: Liberal Arts in Exten., 1962; 1963 (Box 14, Folder 149)
      - New York Univ.: Public Affairs Program, 1959-1961; 1963 (Box 14, Folder 150)
      - Oklahoma, University of, 1961-1968 (Box 14, Folder 151)
      - Washington, University of: Liberal Arts Seminar, 1959-1963 (Box 14, Folder 152)
      - Western Reserve University, 1959; 1961 (Box 14, Folder 153)
      - Wishengrad, Morton (A Cup of Hemlock), 1953 (Box 14, Folder 154)
    - Grantee Evaluations (Box 14)
      - American Education Service, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 155)
      - American Heritage Project: American Library Association, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 156)
      - Film Council of America, 1953 (Box 14, Folder 157)
      - Joint Council on Economic Education, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 158)
    - Green Street (Pasadena) Summer Program, 1952; 1953 (Box 14, Folder 159)
    - Information Releases, 1951-1953; 1960 (Box 15, Folder 160)
    - Lasswell, Harold (Speech), 1959 (Box 15, Folder 161)
    - Library Project Report, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 162)
    - Nelson, Charles A. (Speech), 1959 (Box 15, Folder 163)
    - News Digest, 1959 February-May (Box 15, Folder 164)
    - News Digest, 1959 June-1960 December (Box 15, Folder 165)
    - News Letter, 1951 October; 1952 January-October (Box 15, Folder 166)
    - News Releases, 1951 April 23-1953 April 29 (Box 15, Folder 167)
    - News Releases, 1953 June-1958 (Box 15, Folder 168)
    - News Releases, 1959 January 21-1961 June 6 (Box 15, Folder 169)
    - Parenthood in a Free Nation (Copyright & Agreement), 1961-1963 (Box 16, Folder 170)
    - Patman, Wright, 1961-1968 (Box 16, Folder 171)
    - Project Records (approved and "pending"), Numbers 1-798 (Box 16, Folder 172)
    - Project Records (approved and "pending"), Numbers 802-1479 (Box 16, Folder 173)
    - Report: Adult Education Fact-Finding Survey, 1952 (Box 16, Folder 174)
    - Report: An Exploration into Study-Discussion Activity in the United States, 1958 (Box 16, Folder 175)
    - Seminars (Box 16)
      - Education in a Modern Industrial Democracy: Materials, 1952 (Box 16, Folder 176)
      - Education in a Modern Industrial Democracy: Proceedings, 1952 (Box 16, Folder 177)
    - Special Items, 1956; 1958; 1959 (Box 16, Folder 178)
      memoranda and research proposal